<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tips>
<!--   <menus> -->
	<locale code="en_EN">
		<base_menu>
			<tip key="Install drivers">
				<p>This is the driver installation part.</p>
				<p>Only ".run" packages are managed here and installed from directly</p>
				<p>downlaoded fiLe or from a selected one in user or a local directory</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update drivers or modules">
				<p>This is the update or upgrade driver part.</p>
				<p>Actual or other kernels are managed from there.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Configuration and Tools">
				<p>This part is decated to all edits and configurations.</p>
				<p>It try to cover all user needs, whether for the systtem, Nvidia or Zenvidia.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Help and Documentation">
				<p>All you need to check and/or understand Nvidia drivers is here.</p>
				<p>This part include Nvidia's and Zenvidia's docs and informations.</p>
			</tip>
		</base_menu>
		<menu_install>
			<tip key="From a local package">
				<p>Install a new driver from a user directory local package</p>
				<p>or a already downloaded listed in Zenvidia path.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="From NVIDIA server">
				<p>Will display the full drivers list from the Nvidia server.</p>
				<p>Download and installation will be executed afterward.</p>
			</tip>
		</menu_install>
		<menu_update>
			<tip key="Driver upgrade">
				<p>Download only or install directly could be selected as final process.</p>
				<p>When download only is selected, you need to go afterward to:</p>
				<p>» main menu » Install Drivers</p>
				<p>Note : All download are stored in Zenvidia path.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update driver only (dkms)">
				<p>Install nvidia modules for a new running kernel</p>
				<p>Used to rebuild drivers for the current kernel</p>
				<p>This fonction use only DMKS script.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update driver only">
				<p>Install nvidia modules for a new running kernel</p>
				<p>Used to rebuild drivers for the current kernel</p>
				<p>This fonction use only source directory.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update driver only (force)">
				<p>Optional command to force install from driver sources.</p>
				<p>This is useful in case of DKMS bug or failure.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update driver for an other kernel">
				<p>This command allow to build driver against any other kernel installed in the system.</p>
				<p>This fonction use only source directory.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update driver for an other kernel (dkms)">
				<p>This command allow to build driver against any other kernel installed in the system.</p>
				<p>This fonction use only DMKS script.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Update Cuda Toolkit">
				<p>This command will check Cuda Toolkit update.</p>
				<p>Install is allowed at the end of process.</p>
				<p>Note: because Cuda is taking a huge place, it wont be kept afterward.</p>
			</tip>
		</menu_update>
		<menu_manage>
			<tip key="Edit Xorg config file">
				<p>Edit the current xorg configuration file in /etc/X11.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Edit Zenvidia config">
				<p>Edit Zenvidia basic user conf script to set or unset mostly everything.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Edit Yad GUI colors">
				<p>Change defaults font colors.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Nvidia-settings">
				<p>Start Nvidia-setting graphic UI tool.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Edit Distro config">
				<p>Modify the distribution configation file.</p>
				<p>You can add here very specifics distro's variables.</p>
				<p>Notice: this configuration file edition is optional.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Manage drivers packages">
				<p>This tool is to backup, restore and remove old or current driver install.</p>
				<p>It also manage dowloaded nvidia's .run pack.</p>
				<p>Note: if "backup_prev" option is set and a old installation is found,</p>
				<p>it'd be automatically backed up prior to new version installation.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Zenvidia notification config">
				<p>Configuration tool for Zen_notify daily update checker.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Open driver switch tool">
				<p>(Optional)</p>
				<p>When available, this tool allow to switch between</p>
				<p>open and proprietary source drivers.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="PRIME Display config">
				<p>(Optional)</p>
				<p>When available, manage Prime Display behaviour.</p>
				<p>PRIME and PRIME render offload managed only.</p>
			</tip>
		</menu_manage>
		<menu_infos>
			<tip key="Documentation manual"><p>Read the full current Nvidia documentation file</p></tip>
			<tip key="Change Logs"><p>Read the current Nvidia version changelog file</p></tip>
			<tip key="Zenvidia Logs"><p>Read the Zenvidia changelog file</p></tip>
			<tip key="Zenvidia Help and documentation"><p>Read Zenvidia documentation file</p></tip>
			<tip key="About Zenvidia"><p>Read current Zenvidia README file</p></tip>
			<tip key="Cuda Release Notes"><p>Open dedicated release notes in the browser</p></tip>
			<tip key="Cuda Documentation manual"><p>Open dedicated documentation pages in the browser</p></tip>
		</menu_infos>
		<manage_pcks>
			<tip key="Remove downloaded packages">
				<p>Manage downloaded packages in Zenvidia directory.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Backup tools">
				<p>Make a drivers and libraries backup of the current Nvidia version.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Restore tool">
				<p>Make a restoration of previously backed up drivers installation.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Remove Nvidia and restore to default">
				<p>Remove completly Nvidia Drivers installation and restore to default Nouveau drivers.</p>
				<p>This operation implies certain risks. To usue with high cautions.</p>
			</tip>
		</manage_pcks>
		<net_version_selector>
			<tip key="Looking for latest version">
				<p>Look up for the last available version from Nvidia repos site.</p>
				<p>Will show either official or beta release.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Looking for older version">
				<p>Look up for a previous release available in Nvidia repos site.</p>
				<p>Note that the listing take a little time, we're talking about the whole drivers list.</p>
			</tip>
		</net_version_selector>
		<edit_xorg_conf>
			<tip key="Edit full Xorg (GUI)">
				<p>Edit all non sensitives Xorg option and sets in tabed GUI.</p>
				<p>Tips will popup on each row if available.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Edit full Xorg (text)">
				<p>Edit raw Xorg configuration file in a text editor.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Execute Xorg auto config">
				<p>Re-create Zenvidia Xorg configuration file creation automation.</p>
				<p>This is the same as executed during post-install procedure.</p>
				<p>It's a replay in case a lost xorg.conf files.</p>
			</tip>
		</edit_xorg_conf>
		<zen_notif_setup>
			<tip key="Check driver update only">
				<p>This set will only check driver updates at session start.</p>
				<p>Zenvidia updates will be ignored.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Check zenvidia and driver update">
				<p>This set will check both Nvidia driver and Zenvidia updates at session start.</p>
			</tip>
		</zen_notif_setup>
		<prime_setup_window>
			<tip key="opti_set">
				<p>If set, GPU renderer choice will be set to PRIME by default.</p>
				<p>Only Nvidia dGPU will be used.</p>
				<p>You can changed this set in : > Configuration and Tools > Edit Zenvidia config</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="offload_set">
				<p>If set, this window wont be displayed at the next installation or update cycle.</p>
				<p>All applicable defined sets will be recorded in configuration file.</p>
				<p>You can changed them set in : > Configuration and Tools > Edit Zenvidia config</p>
			</tip>
		</prime_setup_window>
		<set_su>
			<tip key="distribution_name">
			<p>Enter the name of the distribution if not displayed.</p>
			<p>This option is not esdsential. It only for diplaying in main menu window.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="su_commnd_line">
				<p>Select a commande line in the list.</p>
				<p>If your environment SU command prompt is not in scroll list, enter one here.</p>
				<p>Command with full options is mandatory.</p>
				<p>If you're afraid to make a mistake, think to ask your distribution's community first.</p>
			</tip>
		</set_su>
		<from_directory>
			<tip key="Use Zenvidia stock director">
				<p>Every donwloaded packages are stored in default or user Zenvidia directory.</p>
				<p>When available score is always greater than 0.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Use a user local directory">
				<p>Alternatively, you can select a local Nvidia package from user directory.</p>
				<p>As above, score need to be greater than 0.</p>
			</tip>
		</from_directory>
		<backup_tools>
			<tip key="Make a backup">
				<p>Back up the current driver installation.</p>
				<p>It could be a fresh or new a previously backed up archive.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Remove a backup">
				<p>Manage previously archived installation driver.</p>
			</tip>
		</backup_tools>
		<last_driver_pack>
			<tip key="compat">
				<p>This package includes compatibility for 64 and 32 bits librairies.</p>
				<p>Mandatory for programs such as Wine for gaming environment.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="no_compat">
				<p>This package is for pure 64 bits environment.</p>
				<p>To select if you do not intend to run programs needing 32 bits compatibility.</p>
			</tip>
		</last_driver_pack>
		<model_fnc>
			<tip key="first_row">
				<p>1.</p>
				<p>1.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="second_row">
				<p>2.</p>
				<p>2.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="third_row">
				<p>3-</p>
				<p>3s-</p>
			</tip>
		</model_fnc>
	</locale>
<!-- Translation "fr_FR" last date 24/4/26 -->
	<locale code="fr_FR">
		<base_menu>
			<tip key="Installer des Pilotes">
				<p>Ceci est la partie consacrée à l'installation du pilote.</p>
				<p>Seuls les paquets ".run" sont ici gérés et installés depuis un paquet</p>
				<p>directement téléchargé ou depuis répertoire local ou utilisateur.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Mettre à jour les pilotes et modules">
				<p>Ceci est la partie consacrée à la mise à niveau ou à jour.</p>
				<p>Les noyaux actuels ou alternatifs sont gérés à partir de ce menu.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Outils et Configurations">
				<p>Cete partie est consacrée aux éditions et configurations.</p>
				<p>Il tente de couvrir tous les besoins de l'utilisateur</p>
				<p>que ce soit pour le système, Nvidia ou Zenvidia.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Aide et Documentation">
				<p>Tout ce que vous avez besoin pour noter ou comprendre les pilotes Nvidia.</p>
				<p>Vous trouverez ici les informations et documents de Nvidia et Zenvidia.</p>
			</tip>
		</base_menu>
		<menu_install>
			<tip key="Depuis un paquet local">
				<p>Installe un nouveau pilote depuis le répertoire utilisateur</p>
				<p>ou déjà téléchargé et disponible depuis le dépot Zenvidia.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Depuis le serveur NVIDIA">
				<p>Affichera la liste complète des pilotes depuis le serveur Nvidia.</p>
				<p>Le télécahrgement et l'installation seront exécutés après coup.</p>
			</tip>
		</menu_install>
		<menu_update>
			<tip key="Mise à niveau du pilote">
				<p>Vérifie les mises à jour du pilote.</p>
				<p>Vous pouvez choisir durant le processus de télécharger seulement ou d'installer.</p>
				<p>Si vous sélectionnez d'uniquement télécharger le pilote, retournez coup à:</p>
				<p>» Menu principal » Installer des pilotes.</p>
				<p>Note: Tous les téléchargements sont stockés dans le dépôt Zenvidia.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Mettre à jour le pilote uniquement (dkms)">
				<p>Installe des modules dkms nvidia pour un nouveau noyau.</p>
				<p>Utilisé pour re-contruire le pilote courant.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Mettre à jour le pilote uniquement">
				<p>Installe des modules dkms nvidia pour un nouveau noyau.</p>
				<p>Utilisé pour re-contruire le pilote courant.</p>
				<p>Cette fonction utilise uniquement le répertoire source. </p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Mettre à jour le pilote uniquement (forcé)">
				<p>Commande optionnelle pour forcer l'installation depuis les sources pilotes</p>
				<p>Utilisé pour re-contruire le pilote courant dans le cas d'un bug ou échec de DKMS.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Mettre à jour le pilote pour un autre noyau (dkms)">
				<p>Commande optionnelle pour mettre à jour les modules nvidia pour un autre noyau.</p>
				<p>Cette fronctionn utilise DKMS.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Mettre à jour le pilote pour un autre noyau">
				<p>Commande optionnelle pour mettre à jour les modules nvidia pour un autre noyau.</p>
				<p>Cette fonction utilise uniquement le répertoire source.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Misee à jour de Cuda Toolkit">
				<p>Cette commande contrôlera les mise à jour Cuda Toolkit.</p>
				<p>L'installation sera permise à la fin du processus.</p>
				<p>Note: puisque Cuda prend énormément de place, le paque ne sera pas conservé après coup.</p>
			</tip>
		</menu_update>
		<menu_manage>
			<tip key="Éditer le fichier de configuration Xorg">
				<p>Éditer le fichier de configuration courant xorg dans /etc/X11.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Éditer la configuration de Zenvidia">
				<p>Éditer le fichier configuration de base de Zenvidia et toutes ses options.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Éditer les couleurs du GUI Yad">
				<p>Changer les couleurs par défaut des polices.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Nvidia-settings">
				<p>Démarrer l'outil graphique Nvidia-setting.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Éditer la configuration de la distribution">
				<p>Permet de modifier le fichier de configuration de la distribution locale.</p>
				<p>Vous pouvez ajouter ici les variables spéciales de la distribution.</p>
				<p>Information: cette édition est très optionnelle.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Gérer les paquets de pilotes">
				<p>Cet outil permet de sauvegarder, restaurer ou supprimer des pilotes</p>
				<p>anciens ou courants, ainsi que de gérer les paquets Nvidia téléchargés.</p>
				<p>Note: si l'option "back_prev" est activée et qu'une installation précédente</p>
				<p>est trouvée durant la mise à jour du pilote, elle sera automatiquement</p>
				<p>sauvegardée avant l'installation d'une nouvelle version.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Configuration des notifications Zenvidia">
				<p>Outil de configuration pour le contrôle journalier de Zen_notify.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Outil de permutation du pilote Ouvert">
				<p>(Optionnel)</p>
				<p>Quand disponible, cet outil permet de basculer entre</p>
				<p>les pilotes Ouvert (MIT/GPL) et Propriétaire (NVIDIA®).</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Configuration PRIME Display">
				<p>(Optionnel)</p>
				<p>Quand disponible, gére le comportement du Prime Display.</p>
				<p>Pris en charge de PRIME et PRIME render offload uniquement.</p>
			</tip>
		</menu_manage>
		<menu_infos>
			<tip key="Manuel de documentation">
				<p>Lire le fichier documentation intégrale courant du pilote Nvidia</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Journal des modifications">
				<p>Lire le journal courant des modifications du pilote Nvidia</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Journal des modifications Zenvidia"><p>Lire le journal des modifications Zenvidia</p></tip>
			<tip key="Aide et documentation Zenvidia"><p>Lire le fichier de d'aide et de documentation Zenvidia</p></tip>
			<tip key="À propos de Zenvidia"><p>Lire le fichier README actuel de Zenvidia</p></tip>
			<tip key="Note de version Cuda"><p>Ouvre la page de dédiée dans le navigateur</p></tip>
			<tip key="Manuel de documenttaion Cuda"><p>Ouvre les pages de documentation dans le navigateur</p></tip>
		</menu_infos>
		<manage_pcks>
			<tip key="Supprimer des paquets téléchargés">
				<p>Gérer les paquets téléchargés dans le répertoire Zenvidia.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Outils de sauvegarde">
				<p>Faire une sauvergarde des pilotes et librairies de la version Nvidia courante.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Outils de restauration">
				<p>Faire un restoration d'une archive précédemment sauvegardée.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Supprimer Nvidia et restaurer le système par défaut">
				<p>Supprimmer entièrement l'installation Nvidia et restaure au pilote Nouveau par défaut.</p>
				<p>Cette oprération représente un certain risque. À manier avec prudence.</p>
			</tip>
		</manage_pcks>
		<edit_xorg_conf>
			<tip key="Éditer intégralement Xorg (GUI)">
				<p>Éditer les options non sensibles de l'environnement X dans un GUI en onglets.</p>
				<p>Les tips surgiront sur chauqe ligne si disponible.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Éditer intégralement Xorg (texte)">
				<p>Éditer la configuration Xorg brute dans un éditeur de texte.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Éxécuter l'auto configuration de Xorg">
				<p>Rejoue l'automatisme de création de la configuration Xorg par Zenvidia.</p>
				<p>Ceci est la même procédure que durant la post installation.</p>
				<p>C'est un Replay en cas de perte du fichier xorg.conf.</p>
			</tip>
		<zen_notif_setup>
			<tip key="Check driver update only">
				<p>This set will only check driver updates at session start.</p>
				<p>Zenvidia updates will be ignored.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Check zenvidia and driver update">
				<p>This set will check both Nvidia driver and Zenvidia updates at session start.</p>
			</tip>
		</zen_notif_setup>

		<backup_tools>
			<tip key="Faire une sauvegarde">
				<p>Sauvergarder l'installation pilote courante.</p>
				<p>Cela peut être un nouvellement installée ou une archive déjà précédemment traitée.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="Supprimer une sauvegarde">
				<p>Gérer les archives pilotes précédemment sauvegardées.</p>
			</tip>
		</backup_tools>
		<last_driver_pack>
			<tip key="compat">
				<p>Ce paquet inclus les compatibilités pour les librairies 64 and 32 bits.</p>
				<p>Indispensable pour les programmes tel que Wine pour les environnements gaming.</p>
			</tip>
			<tip key="no_compat">
				<p>Ce paquet est purement 64 bits.</p>
				<p>À sélectionner si n'y a pas intention d'utiliser de compatiblités 32 bits.</p>
			</tip>
		</last_driver_pack>
	</locale>
<!--   </menus> -->
</tips>

